[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu tonight
we want to start not start but we want
to continue with the concept of
curvature
I explained to you the idea of curvature
for surfaces surfaces mean
two-dimensional
uh surfaces
let me just review
the basic concept
if you have a curved surface you still
have a concept of parallel transport
you have a concept of going as straight
as possible not deviating to the left
not deviating to the right but
nevertheless the effect of the curvature
will have an effect on the direction of
vectors when they go around closed Loops
if there was they around closed curves
if there was some curvature in uh in the
area that they circumnavigated
so sphere or any kind of curved surface
if we have a curved surface and we
have a curve in that curved surface I'm
using curve in two different senses now
one has to do with the curvature of the
surface the other has to do with the
curvature of a curve uh incidentally a
straight line is a special case of a
curve it's it's a curve without which is
uncurved yeah
so if you go around in a little closed
path and you take a vector start it
somewhere on that closed path now a
vector means a vector that points in the
direction in the surface
roughly speaking you can think of it as
pointing in in the direction of the
tangent plane of the surface so it
points in the direction of the surface
uh that unfortunately looks like it's
pointing out of the surface but I can't
figure out any way to draw a vector that
it won't look like it's pointing out of
the surface so you keep in mind it's in
the surface
and then we transport it parallell to
itself around the closed curve if the
region inside the closed curve is flat
then the vector will come back to itself
if there's some curvature in there then
typically it will undergo some rotation
by some angle
okay that angle let's call it Theta
now there are two senses of angle here
that we have to keep track of question
I have in mind small curves but uh
yeah I'm I'm speaking I'm speaking about
small curves we're going to be taking
the limit of very small curves infinite
infinitesimal curves curves which
contain infinitesimally small area so we
can concentrate on on curves which are
small by comparison with the radius of
the whole uh the whole thing okay and
that's that's the situation we're
interested in curvature is a local thing
in other words you can monitor the
curvature by looking in some small
little region and not going around whole
big uh you don't have to you don't have
to walk around the entire circumference
of the earth to discover that the Earth
is curved if you had sufficient accuracy
you could walk around a small little
area and discover that the uh that the
surface of the Earth is curved yeah so
in this example
yes but I want you to forget that I want
you not to think about that I want yeah
there's no the problem this is a problem
of the architecture of our brains we
simply don't have the architecture to be
able to Envision
surfaces and spaces out of three
dimensions
uh so there's no way I can draw them in
that you have one dimension on top of
two dimensions
that's saying I don't know diens
no no no the thing is we want that
that's exactly what we don't want to
analyze we don't want to analyze the
curvature that's due to the fact that
it's embedded in a curved way in the we
want to ask the question supposing a
little bug lived on this surface
that bug can only receive light from
inside the surface can only see inside
the surface has no capacity to probe in
the direction per pendicular
and can do all sorts of geometrical
experiments
involving little rulers
but rulers which are attached to the
surface parallel to the surface little
protractors which also lie in the
surface and can do geometry on the
surface without ever pointing their
ruler or their protractor out of the
surface
that's the term that comes up is
intrinsic
in other words properties which are
intrinsic to the surface the opposite
are things that has to do with the way
that it's embedded in space and those
are called extrinsic
intrinsic and extrinsic we are now
interested only in the intrinsic
properties
that this very very small bug would
discover by doing um
experimental geometry on the surface
with tool tools that can only lie in the
surface okay all right so we're talking
about the uh the intrinsic curvature of
the surface and the idea of parallel
transport is an intrinsic idea if that
little bug had Wheels
think of a little bug with little wheels
uh little dumbbell-shaped Affair
two wheels
that could roll on the surface if the
wheels had exactly the same size and
they couldn't and of course I'm assuming
that they cannot uh rotate relative to
each other then if I rolled it along the
tabletop here it would describe a
straight Arc right okay uh if I rolled
it across the surface of a sphere it
would move as straight as possible along
the surface of a GE a geodesic in that
case a um a great circle so this is an
experiment
well I suppose you'd say the wheels
stick out of the surface a little bit
but we could make the whole thing
smaller and smaller until the bug uh
until the bug uh the dumbbell bug here
was infinitely small and allow him to
sweep out geodesics across the surface
here
so the idea of a geodesic and not only
the idea of a geodesic but the idea of
parallel transport and the idea of um
covariant derivative are ideas which are
intrinsic
intrinsic that bug could move around
of course we're really thinking about
ourselves as bugs in three dimensions
and we're trying to disconnect the
intrinsic properties of
three-dimensional space from the
possibility that it might perhaps be
embedded in some fourth dimension or
something like that well we wouldn't
want to use uh rollers but we could use
gyroscopes and gyroscopes are things
which only point in our own
three-dimensional space they don't point
out into any hypothetical fourth
dimension
and so exploring space with gyroscopes
uh and rulers and so forth would be
exploring the intrinsic geometry of
three-dimensional space any case one of
the things we can do with gyroscopes is
we can Define parallel transport the
gyroscope will naturally move in a way
which moves parallel to itself and it
does Define parallel transport
physically
it has the same properties as the
parallel transport that we describe
mathematically
in any case we can proceed to parallel
transport that Vector from one point to
another
uh and in fact around in a closed curve
when it goes around in a closed curve it
will not necessarily come back to the
same configuration what'll happen to it
is it will rotate in general
parallel transport does not change the
length of vectors
it changes only their orientation
does not change their uh their length
and so at most what can happen to a
vector is when it comes around it gets
rotated by some angle
okay
now there are two senses of rotation
that we have to keep track of Senses I
mean now senses in the sense of sign s i
GN
first of all there's the direction that
we go around the loop
we can go around one way or the other
way depending on which way we go around
the vector will either shift in One
Direction or in the other direction
that's one sense of angle that we have
to keep track of which direction we
circumnavigated around we took our
vector and we went around let's say
let's say counterclockwise
the other angle that we need to keep
track of is the amount that the angle
deviates
so for example if we go around
counterclockwise
and the vector as it's transported
around the curve gets deflected in the
counterclockwise Direction
counterclockwise
Excursion
produces counterclockwise
rotation
then we say that the curvature is
positive if counterclockwise Excursion
produces clockwise rotation of the
vector we say the curvature is negative
whatever the curvature is it's a single
function on the space and it's simply
defined by going around with your little
probe
measuring let's by definition say we go
around counterclockwise
we measure the angle for small for very
very small
curves here the angle will be small so
let's just call it D Theta the small
change in the angle when we go around
the closed loop and if we divide that
by the small area contained in that
closed loop then we get the curvature
the curvature is the limit
of the deflection angle it's called the
deflection angle
divided by the area as the area goes to
zero because as the area goes to zero
the deflection also goes to zero that's
called the curvature scaler the
curvature and there's a curvature at
every point on the surface
can be positive it can be negative
it's positive on on surfaces that are
spherical like spherik
it is negative on surfaces that are
saddle like saddle shap like
now the situation is clearly more
complicated in higher Dimensions let's
first take three dimensions in three
dimensions
we can proceed around small closed Loops
but we have to orient
the surface somehow for example in three
dimension
I can go around a little Clos curve here
I go around a little Clos curve here I
can go around in this direction I need
to describe an axis
the axis is not the axis of rotation of
the vector the axis is the axis around
which my little bug travels doing his
experiment right so there's one axis in
the problem which we can just say is the
axis
uh
around which the Excursion takes place
so our little bug or our little
gyroscope a little gyroscopic setup in
this case is transported around an axis
now in three dimensions you can use the
concept of an axis to describe a uh uh a
plane the it's just the axis
perpendicular to the plane in higher
Dimensions or in lower dimensions it's
not useful to think of a little closed
curve or a surface as having to do with
an axis
uh it always has to do with two
directions of space
you describe a Plane by picking two
directions of space Direction over here
Direction over here two perpendicular
directions of space Define a plane
it doesn't matter if you're in five
Dimensions 10 Dimensions 20 dimensions
two directions Define a plane and then
you can go around in that plane so you
characterize the Excursion that you go
around by giving two axes as I said in
three dimensions you can replace the two
axes by a third axis which is
perpendicular to it but that's special
to three Direction three dimensions
all right so that's one orientation that
you have to keep track of
the other orientation the other thing
you have to keep track of is a vector
taken around here will typically rotate
but it won't necessarily rotate about
the same axis if I take my
um apparatus the uh the gyroscope my
gyroscopic uh I can take three
gyroscopes all hooked together to define
a coordinate system there and I move
them around and I see how they move uh
how they parall transport and I take
them around an axis around the axis of
my arm
if this curvature in the region of my
arm when I go around to the other side
the a the the axes will have rotated
what axis will these rotate about not
necessarily the axis that you
transported them about for example this
might be the z-axis I might take my
little device here around the z-axis
and discover that it rotated around the
x-axis
so in diagnosing what's going on in
space and understanding the curvature
there are two and three dimensions there
are two axes to keep track of
in general there are two planes to keep
track of the two planes to keep track of
are one of them is the little plane that
you move around in the other one is is
the plane in which the vectors rotate
rotation within a plane
all right so I'm going to write down now
the general formula
uh for
yeah
we take this vector and we C around yeah
the surface and we come up with an angle
ex
that means that the concept of
parallelism which is goes along with
flat is D which means that it's not flat
right if you discover that when you try
can we run into the same problem with
the concept of perpendicularity
no in principle you could imagine
that uh that that does happen that does
not happen in ranian geometry in ranian
Geometry you can imagine more
generalized kinds of geometries apine
geometries other kinds of geometri
um the notion of perpendicularity is an
invariant notion in a remian geometry
things which are perpendicular stay
perpendicular all right that's an
important point that parallel transport
in ranian geometry and in general
relativity is defined in a way that
vectors when you transport them if they
are
perpendicular to begin with they stay
perpendicular
so perpendicularity is an invariant
concept
uh okay so let's write down the general
formula
supposing
now I'm not even going to tell you how
many dimensions we're in because it
doesn't matter it could be 2 3 4 100,000
it doesn't matter pick two axes let's
let's see what I call them
I called one of them
X new and the other one X mu
and now what we're going to do uh and
there're two different axes mu and new
are intended to be different here could
be X and Y it could be x and t it could
be whatever you like we're going to go
around in a small
rectangle
or as close to a rectangle as we can
build
in other words we're going to have a
small DX mu and a small DX new
okay
that characterizes
the Excursion
in the X mu X new plane we go a little
bit along XM and we go a little bit
along X new then we come back along X mu
and then we come back by the same amount
along X new
that creates a little bit of area and
that area will be proportional
to the product of DX mu * DX new
it won't be exactly DX mu * DX new
because I haven't particularly said that
these two directions are perpendicular
and I haven't told you what the metric
is but whatever the metric is the area
in here will be proportional to DX * DX
DX mu new * DX new the area will be
proportional to that and so to begin
with then we have two axes and a little
bit of area in there we carry a vector
we start a vector at one end and we
bring it around and we look at it what
it's done now what are the rules the
rules are we do it by parallel transport
which we've already defined
we'll come back to that definition but
it's the definition involving the
christopal symbols so we parallel trans
that Vector around the curve
okay bringing it back to itself parallel
transporting it means that the uh that
the derivative along that the covariant
derivative along the curve is zero so
you would think it must come back to
itself if the covariant derivative is
zero but the thing is the covariant
derivative is not the ordinary
derivative
and so if we start with a vector v
and we transport it around the closed
curve there will be a change
and that change let's write down a very
general formula
it will be proportional
to DX mu and DX new
why because we expect it to be
proportional to the area that we've
enclosed
so it will be proportional to DX mu and
DX
me on the uh on the superscript for V
you already use oh you're right we
shouldn't DX new DX
so it's going to have DX new and DX
Sigma the X new all right it is going to
also involve the the vector that we
started with it's basically going to be
a rotation of the vector the change in a
vector will be proportional to the
vector that you start with if you start
with a vector which is zero it'll stay
zero if you start with a vector which is
very long it'll stay very long because
its length is preserved and so we expect
that the change in the vector when it
goes around the closed Curve will
involve the vector itself
let's give it an index V Tow
and the rest has to be some object which
defines the curvature it's the curvature
tensor so let's see if we can build a
formula
we have three indices upstairs
one index on the right hand side one
index upstairs on the right hand side on
the leand side here the only thing we
can have here is some tensor
which has an upper index mu to match
this index here
a
new and a sigma and a TOA
all right now you can work this formula
you can work this out yourself all you
have to do
is use the formula for covariant
differentiation
say that along the first curve Co let's
let me write it down do you remember
what the formula for covariant uh
differentiation along a curve is
let's just write it down
uh
it's something like d v mu by DS s is
length along the curve plus
gamma mu
uh
I don't know Alpha Beta
uh times the
V Alpha
times the tangent Vector DX
beta by DS
that was the covariant derivative of the
vector v along the curve parameterized
by S
okay if I want to set that equal to zero
then I have an immediate formula how the
for how V should change along s how the
components of V should change CH change
along S I don't need the DS here the DS
is not playing any role just divide
through by it what it says is that the
change in the vector v going from here
to here is equal to minus gamma Alpha
Beta mu V Alpha DX beta
that's the formula for the change of the
vector in going from here to here
now what do you think the change in the
vector would be if I parallel
transported it to here and then parallel
transported it right back
the answer would be zero no change
parallel transport is not so weird that
when you transport a thing and then
transport it back yeah it doesn't do you
need some area enclosed
in order to get an answer
all right so um if you transport from
here to here you get that when you
transport back you're going to get
something entirely similar except along
a neighboring curve
it's not going to be exactly the same
why not because the christopal symbol
over here and over here are not exactly
the same
they vary a little bit also when you go
from here to here
the change in V does not cancel a change
when you come back along this
Arc of the uh of the rectangle why
because the christopal symbol varies
from here to here
so because the christopal symbol varies
As you move around
by the time you get back the the changes
which is this V mu the change in V mu is
not equal to zero
in fact it's clear that what's going to
come into it are derivatives of gamma
it's the derivatives of gamma the fact
that gamas vary from place to place that
means that you don't cancel out
deviations along one Arc by deviations
along the arc coming back
right
here's the formula
I haven't told you what R is yet I
haven't told you what R is yet but you
see that in order to get something you
have to have a shift along one axis and
a shift along the other axis so it has
to have a DX time another DX
that's clear you have to enclose a
little area
the change in V will always be
proportional to V itself so even when
you go around the closed loop it's going
to be proportional to V itself and what
would you expect R to be made out of
from what I just told you
the derivatives of the christopal symbol
are going to enter into R
this is a tensor equation d x v
Delta V on this side here are
these are all or this is the difference
of two vectors at the same point those
Delta V difference of two vectors vector
and a slightly shifted Vector this is a
tensor equation and this is the
curvature tensor it's the remon
curvature tensor
and what it tells you as I said
is per unit area
it tells you how a vector changes when
it goes around in a closed loop
in fact it rotates the vector rotates
but even if it did something more
complicated than rotating this would be
the formula that you would use
and that's what the curvature tensor is
all about it tells you how vectors fail
to return to their original uh Direction
when you parallel transport them around
the closed curve indication that this
curvature somewhere is inside
okay now uh notice that two of these
indices here new and sigma have to do
with the plane that you moved around in
the X mu and the X Sigma the other two
indices to and mu
have to do they contract or they have to
do with the indices of V itself
ta over here goes with ta over here mu
over here goes with mu over here so two
of the indices have to do with the
directions in space that you go around
and the other two indices have to do
with the vector themselves and tell you
how it changes
all right so that's that's the pattern
that's the that's the structure of
uh
the curvature tensor not the structure
of it but that's what a curvature tensor
is
it's the general definition of the
curvature tensor
and as I said it always has four indices
two of them telling you about the plane
that you're moving around in and two of
them telling you about the plane of
rotation of the vector
that's why it has four indices two to
tell you what the directions you're
moving around in and two to tell you the
plane of rotation if you like that the
vector undergoes
those are the four indices of the remon
tensor this is the remon tensor and I'm
now going to write down
it's too tedious to derive this I've
given you the principles you know how to
parallel transport a Vector around a
closed curve
you could make your closed curve be a
little rectangle you could carry out the
process and find R and I advise it it's
a nice exercise it's not too hard to do
I'm just going to write the answer down
because it's more than uh it's more than
as appropriate to do on a Blackboard uh
in in 10 minutes
but the answer is not hard
uh I memorize that years ago
and uh
no I I I I could write this in my sleep
this uh
uh
okay so let me write down the answer for
you
the remon tensor with index row upstairs
notice that the way I've defined it
it has one index upstairs and three
indices downstairs of course you can
change that you can lower an index of a
tensor by Contracting it with the metric
but the way that it's been defined here
from the definition here it it has one
index upstairs and three indices
downstairs and for some reason I have
used different uh letters but uh it
doesn't matter Sigma mu new same tensor
except I've rearranged the uh the
indices and I'm going to write down what
they are they're in terms of derivatives
of the christopal symbols
and also products of the christophel
symbols
D mu
and then there are two terms
which are just products of the uh mu
Lambda row Gamma New Sigma Lambda
minus
Gamma New Lambda row
gamma mu
Sigma Lambda
okay
that's the remont tensor and as I said
it involves derivatives of the
christopal symbols and uh
and it's not hard to work out
that's it
any questions up till now and um H
you know it's a tensor you actually know
it's a tensor from its definition
um
uh
you know it what well how do you know
it's a tensor
um
the leftand side first of all how do you
how do I know that the left-and side is
a vector it's a difference of two
vectors and it's kind of like a
derivative of a vector isn't it but a
derivative of a vector is not a tensor
the covariant derivative is a tensor but
that's because the coordinates may vary
from place to place if we're comparing
two vectors at the same place at the
same origin then the difference of
vectors is a vector it's only when we're
trying to compare vectors at different
places that the difference between two
vectors or the derivative of a vector
with respect to position may not be a
vect a true Vector itself when we're
comparing vectors at the same point in
other words subtracting two vectors Each
of which refers to exactly the same
point in space
that is a vector okay so the left hand
side is a vector transforms as a vector
DX Sigma DX new are vectors V by
definition assum by assumption V is a
vector
and if an equation like this is true for
any Vector the Assumption here is that
this equation is true for any Vector
that you start with that when you take
it around the closed curve that this is
what you get
if you have a vector equation such as
this this is a theorem if you have a
vector equation like this which is true
for every possible Vector that you can
start with then R must be a tensor so
there's a theorem involved here that R
is a tensor it's not obvious from here
is the second half of that some kind
ofor yes
indeed it is
uh
yes if you think of all right all right
so let me tell you what it is it is some
kind of commutator
um
think of these indices as being Matrix
matri um Matrix indices with a parameter
new over here
all right
all right then uh
then you could here's a matri here's a
matrix here's another Matrix let's see
do I have this right new wait a minute
did I write this correct
uh row
yeah yeah you can see here that there's
a product of matrices the index that's
summed over is Lambda here right and so
you could think of this as the product
of two matrices one that you could call
gamma mu and the other that you could
call gamma new there's hidden indices in
here because each one is a matrix
this one is exactly the same except it's
minus Gamma New * gamma mu
so this is in fact the commutator of two
gamma two uh two matrices
right
uh
and in fact the whole thing is also a
commutator but uh that's a little more
complicated
that's a commment of two covariant
derivatives
is is it obvious that this does not
depend on the directions you took you
started with the thex and the X new and
X
well it does depend but it only depends
through the product DX * DX we're
imagining two different vectors here the
we shouldn't call this DX we should be
more careful here um
these are just two different
displacements DX with an index new and
DX with an index mu
all right two different uh displacements
one over here one over here
um we might have called one of them
Delta
we might have called in fact we might
have done it this way we might have
defin defined the displacement over here
which is Delta X and another
displacement over here which is DX
then we would have put one Delta X and
one DX I'm not sure if that helped
uh but it's proportional to the product
of the two displacements those both Su
over
both Su over yeah so they'll take on all
values yeah the both sum over
question yeah can you illustrate what it
means to keep a vector parallel to
itself and you move in a curved surface
like on the surface of the earth I have
a vector it's parall to the surface how
do I know that I'm keeping it parallel
to itself as I move along the surface of
the Earth
well
as I said
you
along the surface of the Earth it's easy
you just drive straight ahead
you aim your steering wheel straight
ahead you don't care you and you don't
allow yourself to turn it you don't care
whether there are bumps or Curves in the
surface you don't care whether you're
going over mountains through mountain
passes you keep that steering wheel dead
straight ahead and that is the
definition of a geodesic
uh
in other words locally
and small little patches you go
perfectly straight ahead
now um
the technical definition is you find
coordinates locally which are as flat as
possible which means that all of the
first and second derivatives of the
metric are equal to zero and in those
coordinates the vector is constant uh
the derivative of the vector is equal to
zero so the technical definition is in
terms of coordinates
which are chosen to be as close as
possible to cartisian coordinates first
and second derivative of the metric all
equal to zero
in that case the only variation of the
vector will come from the variation of
the vector and not the variation of the
coordinate frame if the first and second
derivatives are all equal to zero
okay look so if I if I move along a
geodesic and the vector moves with the
curvature of the geodesic that's that's
parallel if you if you have a jesc
and you have a vect which is pointing
along the geodesic it will stay pointing
along the geodesic right if you have a
vector which is perpendicular to the
geodesic it will stay perpendicular to
it all right now that's not enough in in
two dimensions that's enough to tell you
exactly what covariant differentiation
means in three dimensions it's not in
particular along a geodesic the problem
in three dire Dimensions is you might
have a geodesic anything which is along
the geodesic
will uh stay along the geodesic but
something which is perpendicular to it
it's not enough to know that it stays
perpendicular to the geodesic because it
could spiral around it so it's a little
more complicated uh uh to uh um
uh
what you can do in higher Dimensions is
you can do the following trick
you can take two neighboring geodesics
take a point
and draw a GE desc through it
ah let's first think about it in flat
space
if I have a geodesic pointing through my
shoulder here there's another geodesic
that also points through my shoulder
there's many of them of course but take
another one which is almost parallel to
the starting one just slightly shift it
at a different angle all right those two
Define a plane
now if I transport a vector along the
geodesic not only will it stay
perpendicular
not only will it stay at the same angle
to the geodesic but it will stay at the
same angle to that plane which is
defined by two neighboring geodesics
is that clear in flat space
yeah okay that almost becomes a
definition in higher dimensional space
you take it could be used as a
definition you take another neighboring
geodesic now neighboring means
infinitesimal angle relative to it they
Define a plane in here
and as you transport along one of the
geodesics the angle relative to that
plane something which is perpendicular
to that plane stays perpendicular to the
plane so you can do uh you can do better
in higher Dimensions with a family of
geodesics a family of geodesics which
all pass through the same point but of
course you don't want to take geodesics
at Wild angles you want to take almost
parallel that gives you a good
definition that gives you another
definition of parallel transport
okay but it does come down to the same
thing in a frame of reference which is
locally as flat as possible it means
that the vector has no derivatives in
that in that frame at that point all
right now this is as I said this is the
definition the geometric definition of
curvature
it's a complicated definition the the
concept may not be so complicated but
the uh the actual mathematical formula
for it is as you can see rather
complicated
uh there's there how many components
does the curvature tensor have
let's say in four dimensional space uh
space time
well yeah four * 4 * 4 * 4 it's not that
bad it's not that bad because there's a
lot of symmetry there are a lot of
redundancies and a lot of symmetry that
you can read off this formula you can
read them off this formula to see the
Symmetry is best it's best to lower this
index I can lower this index the usual
way uh supposing I want to Define r
Lambda Sigma mu new I just multiply by G
Lambda row * R row Sigma mu
all right you can lower and raise
indices using the metric and so there's
nothing special about one index being
raised here I can lower them back down
so that they're all lower indices
uh it's still called the remont tensor
it's the remont tensor with all with all
covariant indices it's in this form that
these symmetries are simplest the
symmetries of this object all right so
uh if you work them out using the
definitions of the christopal symbol
and not it's not hard but it's tedious
it's a little bit tedious there are
simple ways to do it but they all
involve a degree of um
uh sophisticated notation which would
take us beyond what I want to do in this
quarter
uh forms and other fancy uh fancy tricks
question yeah um for the dtha daals r
is is Theta dependent on the direction
of the
Theta is dependent on the direction you
go around go around One Direction you
get Theta being plus if you go around
the other direction you get Theta being
minus
yeah the sign switch
and it's a relationship between the
signs of going around and angle rotating
which tells you whether the curvature is
positive or negative
right and all the components of this uh
curvature tensor can be either positive
or NE negative some of them can be zero
some can be zero and others not be zero
that's uh that's quite uh possible
okay so let me tell you what the
symmetries are
let's see first of all let's remember
it's the two let's see the two middle
indices here
which have to do with the plane that you
go around in the two middle indices
parameterize the plane that you move
around in the new Sigma plane the MU and
Tow indices if I'm not mistaken let's
see do I have this right um let me just
check it
yeah the two middle indices
have to do with the plane that you go
around in and the two outer indices have
to do with the directions of the vector
itself how it rotates
okay so same is true here these two
indices have to to do with the uh with a
plane that you move around in the two
inner indices
all right I'm going to write down the
symmetries I hope I have them right
first of all it's anti-symmetric
with interchange of with respect to
Interchange of Alpha and beta
all right that just says if you
interchange Alpha and beta it's anti-
symmetric it's also anti- symmetric if
you interchange gamma and Delta so it's
also equal to minus r Alpha beta the
original Alpha Beta Delta gamma
anti-symmetric with respect to these two
and anti- symmetric with respect to
those two that's one thing
and the only other important thing
is that it's symmetric
yeah it's symmetric with resp with
respect to taking these indices and
these indices and changing them
interchanging them like so in other
words this is equal to R Gamma Delta
beta Alpha no Gamma Delta Alpha Beta
now these are not going to play any big
role in what we do I'm just giving
putting them down for completeness the
point is that there are a lot of
relationships between the components
there aren't as many as it looks there's
a lot of symmetries between them just
following from the definition in terms
of the christopal symbols and in terms
of the symmetries of the christopal
symbols I believe there are 24
independent ones that's a lot so when
you start doing calculations in general
relativity it's awful
no no they are there are unpleasant um
is it the sign of the permutation in S4
what's that is the sign the same as
whatever the permutation is in in the
symmetric group
no I don't think so
so if you interchange beta and gamma it
doesn't it doesn't become negative
well that's see I've given you all of
the symmetries now we would have to uh
if you interchange gamma and beta I
don't think so I don't think there's any
special symmetry
let's see I'll tell you how many
components there are in two Dimensions
let's make a table and then you can tell
me whether it's anything special
Dimension two
Dimension three
and dimension 4
I have no idea what the answer is in
dimension five I would have to work it
out that can work it out but in
dimension two there is one component
in dimension three there are three
components
and in dimension four there are 24
uh does that strike any Bell
they are equal to factorial no they're
not not
no when you Swit the the rotation around
the loop get a minus sign don't you
you do what when you go around the loop
in the opposite direction from the way
same interchanging yeah
those are the middle two right oh God I
hope I don't have up
you know I think I do um
uh those are the middle two
see let me let me just look at it for a
minute um
row is up here
no I I definitely have something
inconsistent here uh it's
yeah and those have to do with the two
directions that you move in mu and new
all right these two terms here have to
do with the fact that the christopal
symbols vary along the MU and New
Direction so these two mu and new those
are the two that have to do with the
directions here I think I made a mistake
uh this does not look right to me let me
correct it
um
yeah I think this should be R Sigma new
uh
mu
to
V I think I just I think I have a
misprint the the typo in my notes
because you are right that this is clear
yeah it's quite clear this is
anti-symmetric under interchange of mu
and new if I interchange mu and new here
these two will be the same except for
minus sign so it's anti- symmetric under
mu new interchange is that what I said
yeah this is anti-symmetric under mu new
interchange anti-symmetric
it's also anti-symmetric under Lambda
Sigma interchange that I know for a fact
and it's symmetric with respect to
interchanging
Lambda Sigma and mu new so do I have it
right I think that's what I wrote here
I think that's consistent with this
isn't it let's see anti-symmetric with
respect to these two yes anti- symmetric
with respect to these two yes and
symmetric with respect to moving them in
pairs that's correct and somehow what I
wrote down here
uh originally was incorrect so let me
correct it
it should be r with a mu
let's call it Sigma
uh
yeah R
yeah
I think I have it right now because
uh Delta X Delta X tow
yeah
should I go back a step and uh
you want you want to go through it again
another question I didn't think so
question yeah
talk about veran for the surface of the
Earth yeah would that be Dimension two
or Dimension three dimension two and
then so there's one number is that the
radius of the Earth Yep curvature the
numerical curvature is the inverse
square of the radius of the Earth
is
you don't have to know where the center
of the earth is in the case of a sphere
you don't have to know where
okay in the case of a sphere you don't
have to know where and for a sphere the
curvature is just equal to one divided
by the square of the radius of the
sphere
the smaller the sphere the bigger the
sphere is the closer it is locally to
being flat
so the bigger the sphere the smaller the
curvature the smaller the sphere the
bigger the carpage are
yeah uh how do you know that the loop
actually does close upon itself is it
just that the transform works out or
there's some other way to check
uh when you take your your little Loop
and then closes the area how do you
enforce the fact that you do in fact
close the loop
well you describe a little curve that
comes back to itself I'm not sure how
you you you you invent an X of put X on
the ground Sigma such that X of Sigma is
equal to X of Sigma plus little bit
so you invent a function for each one of
the components
you invent functions
which come back to themselves after a
small exerion well it just looked like
if you pick those two uh directions like
coordinates you could imagine that if
you went you know followed coordinates
you wouldn't get that to where you
started uh that's in fact true
but what you're saying is if all right
so what you're saying is if I took a a
vector over here and then took another
Vector over here then parallel
transported this one sorry parallel
transported this one up to here that it
wouldn't quite close and that's true but
the failure to close would be a second
order thing which would be quadratic in
the DXs themselves
and um so the failure to close
would uh be
you would have to correct this a little
bit to make it close but the amount that
you have to correct it by wouldn't
affect any of this it would be a small
correction that would also be
proportional to the area
basically
we're doing here're proving that some of
the internal angles is not
it occurs to me I the um the fact that
this doesn't quite close is connected
with these terms
you it's connected with those terms
uh why those terms there they're there
just because the
can can you look at it
transforming like a tensor and whatever
that departure is basically tells you
yeah yeah you can think of it that way
uh there is another for those who are
mathematically minded I will give you a
very very simple definition of the uh of
the um if you're a little bit
mathematically minded
then
there's an the covariant derivative with
respect to X mu is defined how it's
derivative with respect to X mu
plus gamma mu dot dot uh whatever
uh and it acts as an operator as a
differential operator on vectors it's a
thing which acts on vectors it's a
differential operator contains
derivatives and it contains
multiplication by gamas which are also
matrices and uh actors matrices
the curvature is defined in terms of
commutators of covariant derivatives in
different directions covariant
derivatives in different directions
don't commute with each other
uh and the curvature is defined in terms
of that now that's too abstract a
definition for our class for our class
it's just geometrically
the small change in a vector when you go
around the closed loop it contains the
derivatives of the christopal symbols
and it contains quadratic things in the
christopal symbols and the reason that
it contains christopal symbols is
because it's christopal symbols that
determine how parallel transport Works
how a thing gets parallel transported
from one point to another depends only
on the christopal symbols so that's the
only thing that it could involve
and derivatives of them
okay so that's uh that's a definition
that's worth committing to memory if
you're interested in the subject
uh and I I honestly don't really know
any way to make it simpler than that
I simply memorized it worked it out a
few times for a sphere for a uh for a
cone for a couple of geometries for a
three-dimensional geometry and after a
while you get get familiar with it and
it's a uh it's not as uh remote an idea
but again what it has to do with is
intrinsic properties of the geometry
that are obstructions to its flatness
and to diagnose it you go around in
little closed paths and you see how
things change under a circum navigation
around a little closed path
all right more definitions
they give you these definitions now
because they come into General relative
ity in an important way the geometry of
them is obscure they're not particularly
easy to understand geometric quantities
uh
there's something called the Richi
tensor the Richi tensor doesn't have
four components it has two components
in that sense it's easier than the uh
remont t
but the only way to get the remon tensor
is to know the reachi tensor first and
it's gotten from the Richi tensor by
taking the upper index
here Mu Alpha new and Contracting it
uh what we're doing now let me remind
you
two of these indices have to do with the
two directions that you go around in the
other two indices have to do with a
rotation plane if you take one index
having to do with the circum navigation
and one index that has to do with how
the vector rotates and you contract them
you get What's called the reachy tensor
try to try to Fathom it geometrically is
very hard there's nothing easy to
picture about it if you like it is
simply a tensor that you make by
Contracting you can write it another way
you can write it in terms of the tensor
with all of its indices let's write it
with all of its indices downstairs Alpha
Beta Gamma Delta
then you contract index Alpha with index
gamma by
the metric G
Alpha Gamma
Alpha with gamma you contract them
together sum them and you have a thing
which only depends on B and Delta
it has no simple geometric
uh picture that I know of
it's made out of the remont tensor but
it has only two independent component it
has only two components not two
components two indices
and it's symmetric
the symmetries of the uh the remon
tensor is sure that this is symmetric so
this is also equal to R
Delta beta
that's the REI tensor and it plays a
very very big role in the Dynamics of
gravity even though it is not I I
suspect the reason it took Einstein 10
years to work out the general relativity
was in finding the uh the reachi tensor
because it doesn't have any simple uh
pictorial significance
in any case it is what it is
and it will play an important role in
what comes
re Richi r i CC I how else would you
spell it
depends on what language it is
what was Richie's
problem that he had to come up you know
I don't know
you know that's I've looked that up
several times and I could never find out
I don't know oh oh oh okay no I'll
yeah in three dimensions Richi was
interested in three-dimensional space in
three dimensions the Richi tensor and
the reman tensor are completely
equivalent to each other and I'll tell
you why it's it's very simple in three
dimensions a plane is in one to one
correspondence with an axis
so if I have a thing which depends on a
pair of planes that's four indices all
together that's four indices two for
each plane because a plane is the same
as an axis perpendicular to it it's can
also be thought of as a thing which
depends on only two vectors so a thing
which depends on two planes
in three dimensions can be thought of as
a thing which depends only on two Vector
directions the Richi tensor is the way
of describing the reman tensor when you
describe it in terms of axes instead of
planes takes two directions to Define a
plane
and so four directions to define a pair
of planes
but in three dimensions it's simpler it
really only takes two axes so uh I
believe that Richi discovered this form
of it
uh by um
when he was working in three dimensions
why it turns up to be so important in
the theory of gravity we'll come to that
but uh it's not because it has any easy
to picture geometry to it
okay we've we've covered the idea of
curvature as much as I can cover it in
one uh one hour
um geometry
is half of the theory of gravity the
other half of the theory of gravity is
matter
mass
mass affects geometry
Mass curves geometry
John Wheeler used to like to say he had
a phrase a slogan
um Mass curves geometry and geometry
tells uh particles how to move or
something like that I don't remember it
it was more elegant than that but uh the
idea being that the presence of mass
affects geometry
that's another way of saying the
presence of mass creates gravitation
field and gravitational field affects
the motion of particles so they affect
each other particles masses affect the
gravitational field that means that they
affect geometry and geometry affects the
way particles move
uh the curvature incidentally
is the as we'll see is the analog in
general relativity of tidle forces in
Newtonian gravity it's the thing that
you can't remove it's the obstruction
that you can't remove by a coordinate
transformation so think of it that way
and and we'll see more clearly how it
works as we go along all right I want to
Define some Notions which are important
uh
not only in general relativity but in
field theory in general we've talked
about them in earlier classes
let's begin with electric charge
electric charge is a typical thing which
can flow which has a density which has a
flux a flux means a current of it and uh
which is a material quantity that uh
that uh has a uh
sense of being a substance if you like
all right first of all let's take a
a box of space small box of ordinary
space now this is not SpaceTime not
space time I'll tell you when it is
spacetime not SpaceTime just ordinary
space and now let's imagine the world is
full of charged particles tiny tiny
charged particles smoothly distributed
and I can ask what is the total charge
in the Box the total charge in the Box
total electric charge in the Box let me
call some the box is going to be taken
to be small in the end I'll call charge
Q is charge
the amount of charge in the Box will
call DQ because the box is small and of
course it will be proportional to the
volume of the box
but if I divide let's call the volume of
the Box let's call it DV a small box
infinite small box divide the charge by
the volume and I get the density let's
call it row now this is the density not
of mass but the density of charge so
I'll just put a little Q down there to
remind you that it's the density of
charge not the density of mass
that's if you like the definition of
charge density it's go to a go to a
particular point take a small box take
the total amount of charge in it divided
by the volume shrink everything to zero
and the limit is the density
it follows of course that the total
charge in a finite box is the integral
of the density over the box
so that's charge density let me picture
it another way I want to now picture it
in four-dimensional a four-dimensional
picture unfortunately I can't draw a
four-dimensional boxes very well so what
I'm going to do is think of the
threedimensional
box as being two-dimensional
here we're going to now we are going to
draw space time here's time here's Space
X and Y
and unfortunately I cannot draw I can
draw another axis but it would only make
things a little more complicated than
they need to be so let's imagine another
axis but not draw it what does this box
look like it gets it just becomes a
little square a little square in space a
little little square it's not really a
square it has three dimensions but due
to the limitations of the Blackboard and
our brains I will simply draw it as a
little square with two directions X and
Y and implicitly a third Direction now
there are charged particles charges
don't disappear charges are conserved a
charge moving around in the SpaceTime is
just a world line that never begins
never ends because charges don't come
and go and now we can imagine asking how
many charged lines how much charge
passes through
this box
that's just another way of asking at a
given instant of Time how much charge is
in the Box
how much charge is passing through the
box
in A Spacetime sense is equivalent to
the question how much charges in the box
at a given instant of time we could
follow the box of course we could follow
the Box in time
here's the Box same box a little bit
later
is the charge in that box necessarily
the same no because charge can enter the
box over here but then go out here
and not pass through the upper box
that's just another way of saying that a
charge can move out of the box
right so charge is conserved but that
doesn't mean the amount of charge in the
Box in a particular box stays the same
all right so that's the notion of charge
in a box charge density and here I've
drawn the charge density in a way that
makes it seem as though it has something
to do with Charges going through a box
all right so that's row now let's talk
about the current the electric current
the electric current is a similar kind
of idea now you take now we're going
back to space let's go back to space and
forget space time for a moment and let's
draw
a square now I don't mean a
three-dimensional box I mean a
two-dimensional box a a window think of
it as a window there's no window on the
wall here but think of it as a window
and think of the actual motion of
charges as they move
and pass through the window some charges
will pass through the window some
charges will not pass through the window
take the charges which pass through the
window
how much charge will pass through the
window well it's going to be
proportional to the area of the window
but what else what else might it be
proportional to besides the area of the
window
the time the amount of time right so
this's is a flux of charge and the
amount of charge through the window
per unit time is related to What's
called the current so let's write that
the amount of charge
that goes through the window and I'm
going to call the window now a small
window with a differential area da
per unit time
what do I call that I'm going to call
that the current
but this area has an orientation
the area
has a normal Vector to it so I'm really
talking about the charge for example
flowing in a given direction through a
window perpendicular to that direction
it's got a vector index attached to it
so for example if this is the X window
the X window means a window in the YZ
plane if this is the X window the charge
going through the X window per unit time
is called J
X
it's called JX
J is the symbol for Char for for for
current it's called the current you can
call it the flux of charge the current
of charge the flow of charge whatever
you like but it's the charge through a
window perpendicular to X
in per unit time and likewise for JY and
JZ
if you want to know what JY is you take
your window oriented perpendicular to
the Y AIS and you ask how much charge is
going from the negative side of the y-
AIS to the positive side of the Y AIS
per unit time and that becomes JY
now notice both row
and J are charges per unit
how do we say this how many powers of a
length does a volume have three now
remember that time and length are
measured in the same units we are going
to set through out the speed of light
equal to one time has units of length so
how many times how many units of length
are in the denominator here
also three the only real difference
between these
is here I have charge per unit
threedimensional space likee directions
here I have charge per two spacelike One
timik Direction
so these are clearly closely similar
kinds of things charge per unit length
cubed if you like
you can think of the window
as being the window persisting for a
length of time T
that has an area Delta x * Delta y but a
duration of time delta T you can think
of it as being like a volume a
three-dimensional volume but a
three-dimensional volume with one of the
directions being time so both the flow
of charge and the uh density of charge
are components of a single thing a
single thing of a flow of charge through
various kinds of Windows
this window is a space space space
window this window is a space space time
window there are no windows which are
time time space because there's only one
direction of time so this is all the
kinds of Windows there are and these
objects form together to form a four
Vector
it's natural to group them together into
a four vector and that four Vector is
called
the current the four-dimensional charge
current you group together row
JX
j y and JZ
and those you just call J mu
in other words the the charge density
becomes the time component of a four
Vector
the other three components
are characterized by the direction of
the flow of charge and if charges are
just sitting still it's as though
they're moving in time if you like you
can think of it that way a thing which
is sitting still is still moving through
SpaceTime and it's passing through these
windows in SpaceTime and so row together
with J form a four Vector of current
I'm going through this rapidly because
we did it last quarter
uh the idea of the four Vector of charge
how do we express the notion of charge
conservation
the continuity equation everybody
remember the continuity equation I'll
remind you what it is
the continuity equation is the basic
equation I don't want to erase this I
want this there is the basic equation
which
tells us a little more than just the
charg is conserved
if charge is conserved in the whole
universe it just says the amount of
charge in the whole universe doesn't
change but there's a little more to
charge conservation than that I explain
this to you more than once we'll do it
once again though if a charge
disappeared over here and reappeared on
the moon then an instantly we would say
charge was conserved
but an experiment taking place in this
room would be clearly deceived into the
idea that charge is not conserved
it doesn't really work that way we don't
get deceived into the idea that charge
is not conserved for some reason and if
you don't like the Earth Moon you say
well we could always do experiments
involving the Earth and the Moon make it
the Earth in alpha centuri or the Earth
in the next galaxy over whatever you
like it's quite clear that charge
conservation
by itself really doesn't have any real
implication for experiments done in
finite volume
the real notion of charge conservation
is what's called local charge
conservation it doesn't mean that the
amount of charge in the room doesn't
change it means that any change in the
charge in the room is due to observable
flows of charge through the walls the
only way the charge can change in the
room is if it flows through the walls so
an increase in charge would correspond
to a flow of charge in a decrease of
charge in the room would correspond to a
flow of charge out one mathematical
object is there that could represent the
flow of charge radially out outward from
a point
the Divergence
the Divergence is the mathematical
quantity which expresses the idea of a
flow outward
so if you take a small region of space
and you ask how much charge is in it or
not so much how much charge is in it but
how does the charge change with time
well the charge that's in that small
region is the volume of the small region
let's take the volume to be fixed and
let's set it equal to one for Simplicity
then the charge in that small unit
volume is row
I could multiply it by the volume but
I'm setting the volume equal to one in
any case I'm going to hold it fixed all
right now how does that charge change
well it changes by Charges going into
and out of the room but let's take the
time derivative of it
if there's a Time derivative to the
charge density it must mean that there
is a current at the boundary
but that current for example a uniform
current flowing straight through in the
X direction that would do nothing
because there would be as much current
coming in from one side is going out the
other it's the Divergence of the current
which tells you the charge nit charge is
passing out so if if the charge charge
is increasing
then that must mean charge is coming in
it must mean the Divergence is negative
the right equation is that
the change the change per unit time of
the charge density
plus the Divergence of the current now
this is the three-dimensional current JX
JY JZ must be equal to zero what it
expresses is that the rate of change of
charge in the box
is equal to the negative of the amount
of charge that's flowing out of the box
if the charge is Flowing out of the box
the amount of charge must be decreasing
we can write this explicitly it says
that let's say partial of row with
respect to T the partial of row with
respect to T and then what is the
Divergence of the current
anybody remember the form for the
Divergence of a vector
right it's the derivative with respect
to X of the X component plus the
derivative with respect to Y of the Y
component JY
JY
plus the derivative with respect to Z of
j z and that's equal to zero but if I
now call Row
the time component of J we can just
write this as J KN the time component
and we can call T
the time component of the four Vector of
position
this becomes X1
1 2
2 3
three
in other words the continuity equation
just becomes the very simple nice
looking equation that the derivative of
J mu
with respect to X mu is equal to zero
sum over mu
two basic basic kinds of definitions
definition of current in density
and the continuity equation that's the
basic ingredient that goes into the
conservation of electric charge or any
other kind of charge that's conserved
okay now one thing about charge is that
charge itself the components of the
current of charge are a four Vector but
the charge itself how about the charge
itself supposing I have um what are the
units of charge anyway kums huh yeah Kum
is a huge amount of electric charge
if you could somehow assemble a Kum of
charge on this table you would want to
get far out of the room because uh
okay supposing I say there's a coolum of
charge on the table over here and
supposing you're moving by on a railroad
train how much charge would you say is
there
Kum
charge is an invariant it's a scaler if
you like charge is a scaler uh the
charge current is not the charge current
and density are not scalers but the
charge itself the total amount of charge
that's there is a scaler
uh
and so you should afraid of a k of
charge what's that why were you afraid
of a Kum
well that's so much charge that the
repulsive force uh
um here's what I mean Kum charge is what
about 10 to the 19th uh I think it's 10
to the 19th electrons if I remember
okay so you say okay you have 10 to the
19th atoms 10 to the 19th atoms has 10
to the 19th hydrogen atoms has 10 to the
19th electrons who's afraid of uh 10 to
the 19th atoms of hydrogen but now take
those 10 to the 19th atoms of hydrogen
and remove the protons
then you have 10 to the 19th electrons
and that is a highly explosive uh
situation with all the electrons
repelling each other they would repel
each other and just make a huge
explosion I had no trouble putting that
amount of charge in a onead capacitor on
your desk
uh whole Kum oppos
they close together I have no trouble
putting it in a one capacitor on New
Testament I go to fries and buy it
uh
no no no no no no no on the plates both
positive and negative very close
together yeah that's right yeah you have
a positive and negative charges right
next to each other I can charge up the
capacitor to one volt it has one Kon in
it Char It Go Boom it doesn't go boom
okay
10 to the 19 electron a lot of electrons
I don't that's only 10 to 19 electron
BTS which 19 electrons would be that's
about that's only
that's 10 to 19 EVS that's one that's 10
the that's a lot of
it's a nice bang but it's not like yeah
it's a bang
shut yeah no I I don't mean it would
explode the world I mean it would make a
a nice little explosion nice little you
have to do something with it as I say
you go to friy and for a buck you buy
one pair of capacitor and you charge it
up to a h and you've got a Co sitting
right there on your desk you got two KS
you got no you've got no Coons you got
one Co of positive charge one Co of
negative charge next to each other are
you saying there's no energy in the
capacitor no no there's energy in the
capacitor but the energy in the
capacitor depends on the distance
between the capacitor plates pull those
plates if you were to take the capacitor
plates far away you would make a big
energy
yes I was objecting to your saying that
a coolum of charge in your desk is
something to be afraid of a CO of charge
uncompensated by a PO of opposite charge
would be would be uh I think that would
be fairly dangerous
whoes
capacitor has two kind has two plates
positive and negative they cancel each
other
let's put it this way if you to take a
if you were to take a cubic centimeter
of water
a Kum of charge is 10 I think it's about
10 to the 19th electrons that would mean
like something like about one part and
10 the fourth of the atoms had been
ionized
that would be 10 okay so one part and 10
the 4th of the atoms 10 the 23rd atoms
10^ the 19th electrons that would mean
one part and 10 to the so that would be
10 to the n 10 to the 10 to the 19th
electrons that would be 10 to the 19th
electron uh 10 to the 20th electron
volts about ionizing one hydrogen atom
takes about 10 electron volts
so that would be about 10 to the 20th
electron volts how bad is 10 to the 20th
electron volts no it's it's actually not
that bad but uh but it's
it's a noticeable perturbation
it's a noticeable perturbation 10 to the
20th electron volts is like the highest
cosmic ray energy that can hit you it's
100 million
100 million te right but only one
particle it's not like an accelerator
beam hitting you so it's one particle
with a 100 million tev
that's about the highest energy cosmic
ray so if you get hit by a high high
high high energy cosmic ray it can do
some damage uh you're right it's not
it's not a big explosion but it's I
think it's an unpleasant event taking
place in your body
uh
anyway let's go on
all right now let's come to energy
energy and momentum energy and momentum
are also conserved quantities they're
like charge in that respect they're
conserved
but energy and separately momentum
themselves
not their currents and not their flows
or not their densities but the to total
energy and the total momentum of a
system are not scalers are not
invariants this is more or less obvious
if I have an object here standing at
rest and I tell you that its energy and
remember keep in mind e equal mc² so M
and uh c m and E are similar things okay
this object has a certain amount of
energy namely it's mass time c^ s and
now somebody's going on on a really fast
Railroad train going past it
they will see the mc^ 2 plus the kinetic
energy of the uh of the Eraser so energy
is not something that all observers will
agree about
total energy is not an invariant it's
not a scaler neither is total momentum I
say the momentum of this is zero you
going by in the railroad train will say
the momentum is not zero so energy and
momentum are not they are conserved but
they are not uh
invariance
and together
the energy and the momentum of a system
also form a four Vector
we've gone through this when we studied
relativity more than once
the energy of a system again speed of
light equals one
the energy of a system and the momentum
the momentum is a three Vector
it has three components
the energy and the momentum of a system
together form a four Vector the energy
being the time component
and the momentum being the space
components so you can if you like think
of the energy as the time component
and the momentum
X YY and Z as the space components
of another four vector
but this time it's not the four Vector
of density and flow the total quantity
of momentum or the total quantity of
energy of a system together form a four
Vector
the four Vector is conserved each
component of it is conserved
each
[Music]
yes the X component the momentum is
conserved the Y component the momentum
is conserved the energy is conserved so
there are four separate conservation
laws
okay now again
energy conservation and momentum
conservation would be operationally
useless
if it was just that energy could
disappear at one place and reappear on
Mars
it would be operationally useless in
this laboratory
so again there was a notion of a flow of
energy same thing a flow of momentum and
it's the same kind of thing changes in
the energy of a system of a closed
system like this can only happen if
there is a flow of energy or momentum or
whatever it is through the walls of a
system
and so there must also be a notion of a
density of energy
and a flow of energy that's likewise for
momentum let's give them some names and
then let's see if we can make a guess as
to what kind of quantity
the density and flow of energy and
momentum is
I warn you now that I am setting the
speed of light equal to one so some of
the formulas May differ from elementary
textbooks in which there are speeds of
light floating around you can always
restore the dimensions by fig by making
the dimensional analysis consistent but
all right energy first of all is a
notion of the density of energy energy
in a volume divided by the volume take
the volume small defines a uh quantity
which is the density of energy let's
give that a name energy is the time
component of something remember energy
and momentum form the four Vector P P1
P2 P3
so first of all it's a density of
something
and let's label this quantity
by what who who it's who it is we're
talking about we're talking about energy
and energy I'll simply use a shorthand
notation the time component of the four
Vector so energy is a Time component of
something this T is going to be like is
going to be the analog of a density it
is a density it's the density of energy
but let's go back over here where is it
uh yes up here notice that the density
itself quite apart from whatever it's
the density of the density is also the
fourth component of something
so this is the density of energy is the
density of the fourth component in other
words it's the fourth component of a
fourth component
it's the fourth component because it has
to do with energy and it's the fourth
component because it's a density
all right it's Fourth component because
it's a density and density is like the
time component of a flow
so we'll give it two zeros
two zeros because it's the fourth
component of a fourth component now what
about the flow of momentum if we were
talking about charge the flow of
momentum in the X direction would be
called J1
we're now talking about the flow of
something whose name is not
just to label the fact that we're
talking about energy we put a not there
but it's a flow of energy in the One
Direction so we need to put a one there
T1
is the flow of the the zero component of
the energy momentum four Vector in other
words the energy along the x axis
how about uh what would T to mean
that would be the flow of energy along
the two axis
and so forth
okay that takes care of energy and its
flow
what about the X component of momentum
the X component of momentum is just
another quantity which is conserved we
ought to give its density a name how
much X component of momentum is in this
volume well I don't know how much is it
depends on on the microscopic particles
but if there was a flow of particles
through the volume there might be an X
component to the uh
all right so let's talk about the X
component of momentum what should I call
its density
right
this indicated it was a density this
indicated it was the energy all right so
now let's write a t which this index is
now one because we're talking about the
X component of momentum but we're still
talking about its density
so the first index tells us who we're
talking about the second index tells us
what direction the flow is in the flow
is in the time Direction it's a dens it
so this is the density of X component of
of momentum the amount of X component of
momentum in a volume how about the flow
of X component of momentum can you
imagine a flow of X component of
momentum
yeah that's easy I mean you just have
some particles uh going along the uh
they have X component of momentum and
moreover the X component of momentum is
Flowing so along the x- axis this
becomes T1 because we're talking about X
component of momentum but now we're
talking about the flow along the One
Direction
how about a flow of X momentum along the
y direction does that make sense
well supposing I had all there's my x-
Axis there's my y AIS supposing I have a
bunch of particles moving off in an
oblique Direction they are carrying X
momentum from one value of y to another
value of y a bunch of particles going
off that way are taking they also have
some y momentum but in particular they
have some X momentum but that X momentum
is being transported along the Y AIS so
yes it does make sense to talk about the
transport
or the flux or the flow of X momentum
along the Y AIS and along the z-axis
okay what comes next well the next thing
that comes is the Y component the
momentum the density of the Y component
of the momentum is T20
and then the flow along the one axis
t21
t22
t23
and finally T30
t31
T3
to t33
these are the four sets of objects 1 2 3
4 each composed of four pieces itself
which represent the flows and the
densities of the components of energy
and momentum this whole object
is a tensor
now is it obvious that it's a tensor no
it's not obvious that it's a tensor
uh
we will have to do some more work to
convince ourselves that it ought to be a
tensor but it's called the energy
momentum tensor
and we can write it in the condensed
notation team you new
isn't it obvious that it's a tensor
because it's a physical thing yeah
yeah I I would say that uh that's
I I guess the right way to say it is it
better be a tensor or else it's not a
physical thing
uh so and and you write it this way
because each compos is Con unlike the
charge equation yeah each well first of
all this in itself doesn't say that each
component is conserved it just says that
each that they exist now we can ask what
does it say to say that they're
conserved okay so
let's uh make our best guess as to what
it would say that they are conserved
let's look at the at the uh
at the energy
what I want to do is write down for the
energy itself which is just the first
row here I want to write the analog of
the continu it equation in fact I'm
going to write the continuity equation
the first index here that's completely
passive it just says that I'm talking
about energy
the second index tells me whether I'm
talking about density or X or Y or Z
component of flow
okay so if I just mimic or just parot
the top equation there mimic the top
equation
uh for energy what what will it say it
will say that the derivative
with respect to T why don't you pair it
the bottom line I will do all of them
all right but it says the derivative of
T of the
energy density plus the derivative of x
with respect to the flow along the x
axis
plus the derivative with respect to Y of
t y I'm getting tired of writing them
but you see the pattern
I guess we could call these 1 2 and
three
equals zero
all right now I could do the same thing
for the next line the next line is also
a refers to a conserved quantity it
refers to the X component of momentum
the only way the X component of momentum
can change in the room is if x component
of momentum flows through the walls of
the room same deal
so we will write the same equation
except wherever I see nor the first
entry I will write
one then not and so forth and so on I'm
getting a little tired of writing it d
by DX
t11
plus d by Dy
T12
plus d by DZ
t13
no t yeah t13
equals z and likewise for the Third how
many uh there are two more equations
like this each one of these rows has a
continuity equation associated with it
now I can also write this in a single
common notation like this and it is just
of exactly this form d by DX mu
of T new mu equals z
new here is the index which tells us
what we're talking about
energy or first component the momentum
or second component the momentum or
third component in other words it just
names the quantity we're talking about
it's the MU index here which tells us
which direction we're talking about and
gets combined with a derivative here
that's the conservation of energy
equation
local conservation of energy in special
relativity
you say why special relativity and why
not general relativity the answer will
come to next time the equation is
slightly modified in general relativity
the way that it's modified is the
derivative becomes covariant derivative
you say why not covariant derivative
over here
we'll come to that we come to it it is
covariant derivative some slippery
trickery happens here that doesn't
happen here
uh but this is the basic idea of energy
momentum conservation
okay so now we have the basic
ingredients for the general relativity
we have geometry which represents
gravitational field and we have energy
and momentum
which represent the source of the
gravitational field normally we think of
the source of the gravitational field as
as mass
but eal mc²
so if C is equal to 1 energy and
momentum sorry energy and mass are the
same thing so it's natural to think of
mass as the uh source of the
gravitational field but on the other
hand energy or mass comes together with
these other things called momentum
If energy is the source of something
about the gravitational field then in
some other the frame of reference where
energy gets mixed up with momentum
momentum will become the source of some
piece of the gravitational field so
Einstein's job was to figure out how to
write tensor equations which expressed
the sense in which the gravitational
field was sourced by energy and momentum
and to write them in a way that made
good sense in any frame of reference
uh
I'm going to we're not going to do that
today that's a little beyond what I want
to do today I did want to do one more
thing today
I don't know are we really shot or is
there time for
all right one more thing we'll do
now we're coming
I've set up the basic ingredients
for thinking about energy and momentum
as the source of the gravitational field
all it will take is an equation which
has on one side something to do with the
geometry what's it going to be it's
going to be the curvature tensor the
curvature tensor on one side and on the
other side of the equation it will be
the energy and momentum curvature caused
by energy momentum that's half of the
story that tells us how energy and
momentum curves space the other half of
the story is what geometry does to the
motion of particles I want to spend a
little bit of time on that and because I
don't want to have to do it next time
although we'll go probably wind up going
through it the next time the basic rule
that Einstein settled on
for the motion of particles through a
gravitational field is that they move on
geodesics they move in the simplest
possible way particles have little
steering wheels but the steering in
wheels are locked in the Straight Ahead
Direction but not just in space but
through space time SpaceTime has a
geometry
it's described exactly the way we've
described it up till now with a metric
tensor a curvature tensor the whole
story goes through
and particles move through SpaceTime on
SpaceTime geodesics that was the
principle a very very simple principle
what would it say in flat SpaceTime
in flat space time it would say that
particles move through space time on
straight lines
that has two pieces to it it first of
all means that they move along
trajectories in space which are straight
but it also says that they move with a
constant velocity a straight time a
straight line in SpaceTime is something
which moves in a fixed Direction but
with a fixed speed so the principle that
a particle moves on a GE desc in flat
space time would just say that an object
moves with no acceleration
now of course that's ignoring all the
other kinds of forces in the world but
if all we had was gravitational forces
that would be correct
what's the analog of that more generally
more generally the statement is that
particles move on geodesics the
straightest possible paths let me remind
you what the equation for a geodesic is
it's just the equation of Z Z covariant
derivative of the tangent Vector the
tangent Vector is DX mu by D
to being proper time along the
trajectory that's the tangent vector
and to differentiate it with respect the
TOA now we have a tangent Vector along
the along the curve the tangent Vector
is doing whatever it's doing and now
we're asking how the tangent Vector
changes as we move from point to point
well that's another derivative with
respect to too
but that's not the covariant derivative
of the tangent Vector the covariant
derivative of the tangent Vector
involves the christopal symbol
and it's plus
gamma mu new Sigma tangent Vector DX new
by D
tangent Vector DX Sigma by D to
this tells us what the orbit of a
particle is
in space time it's a differential
equation telling us in terms of the
Christal symbol
what the motion is
now I want to restrict myself we have
five more minutes I'm going to go
through this again but I want to do it
now to give you some food for thought
supposing we're in the limit
where Newton is almost exactly right
what does that mean it means that the
gravitational fields are not too strong
and it also means that things are moving
slowly
all right it means that everything is
moving slowly
in fact I'm beginning to move slowly
I think we're going to come back to it
next time I think we're too close to the
uh yeah all right if you want to do if
you want to uh if you want to play with
this a little bit see if you can say see
what this says here's the here's the
goal
put in the fact that all the particles
are moving slowly
okay that means that DX by DT not D to
but d x by DT is small the ordinary
velocities of particles are small
are there any components of DX by D to
which are not small
yeah the time component because the time
component is almost exactly equal to one
it's ESS essentially DT by DT almost
equal to one so when particles move
slowly only the time components of these
tangent vectors are appreciable
right now
uh to and T are almost the same if
particles move slowly so this is almost
the ordinary acceleration
this is almost the ordinary acceleration
on the right hand side here these things
are either very small or they're close
to one so what does it say it says the
acceleration
is equal to the christopal symbol to a
certain christopal symbol the christopal
symbols
evidently are the gravitational field
they're the the gravitational
acceleration they're like the things we
called in the beginning a the field of
acceleration
so this is the connection here's how
we're going to make the connection
between Newton's equations Newton's
second law of motion and Einstein's
principle that things move on geodesics
these are negligibly they're essentially
one when this is time components
and the gamma
becomes uh which gamma is important here
what are the relevant indices here
remember that the X by the TOA is only
appreciable if it's a Time component so
that means that the gravitational force
is basically just gamma
mu0
the gravitational force along a given
Direction let's say the y direction is
the christopal symbol gamma y 0 0 that's
going to be the link to guide us to um
to the motion of well to the connection
between uh various gravitational things
and other things in Newton's equations
might as well write it down right now
the field of acceleration is equal to
the christopal symbol we'll come back to
that and then we'll try to put the whole
thing together and find equations which
express
uh the connection between the
gravitational field and the masses on
the one hand and the uh gravitational
forces on particles on the other hand
[Music]
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu